Finding Aid for the Laura A. Kalpakian Papers LSC.1342
UCLA Library Special Collections
Laura A. Kalpakian papers
circa 1980
UCLA Library Special Collections
Kalpakian, Laura
LSC.1342
10.5 Linear Feet (21 boxes)
Laura Anne Kalpakian (b.1945) has worked as a professor of English and writing, book critic, and free-lance writer. Her major works include: Educating Waverly (2002), The delinquent virgin (1999), Steps and exes: a novel of family (1999), Cosette: the sequel to Les Misérables (1995), Graced land (1992), Dark continent and other stories (1989), Crescendo (1987), Fair Augusto and other stories (1986), and Beggars and choosers (1978). Her stories and essays have also appeared in literary anthologies and serial publications, including Cosmopolitan, McCalls, Los Angeles times, and Hawaii review. The collection is composed of Kalpakian's manuscript materials, including drafts, research notes and materials, and correspondence with editors and publishers, for published and unpublished works, and a small amount of printed material.
Restrictions on Access
Written permission of Laura A. Kalpakian needed for access.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
COLLECTION CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access digital materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Laura A. Kalpakian, 2003.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9948888193606533
Biography
Author and critic Laura Anne Kalpakian was born June 28, 1945, in Long Beach, California. She grew up in southern California. Kalpakian received her undergraduate degree from UC Riverside in 1967. She briefly took a job as a social worker before continuing her education at the University of Delaware, where she completed a masters degree in 1970. Kalpakian attended the Ph.D. program in literature at UC San Diego, from 1973-1977. She has worked as a professor of English and writing, book critic, and free-lance writer. Kalpakians major works include: Educating Waverly (William Morrow, 2002), The delinquent virgin (Graywolf Press, 1999), Steps and exes: a novel of family (Bard, 1999), Caveat (John F. Blair, 1998), Cosette: the sequel to Les Misérables (HarperCollins, 1995), Graced land (Grove Weidenfeld, 1992), Dark continent and other stories (Viking, 1989), Crescendo (Random House, 1987), The swallow inheritance (Headline, 1987), Fair Augusto and other stories (Graywolf Press, 1986), These latter days (Times Books, 1985), and Beggars and choosers (Little, Brown, 1978). Works produced under a different name are Belle haven (Viking, 1990), written under the pseudonym Juliet Jackson, and Tiger hill (Piatkus Books, 1985) written under the pseudonym Carenna Jane Gray. Kalpakian's stories and essays have also appeared in literary anthologies and serial publications, including Cosmopolitan, Good housekeeping, McCalls, Los Angeles times, The Miami herald, and Hawaii review.
Scope and Content
The collection is composed of manuscript materials, including drafts, research notes and materials, and correspondence with editors and publishers, for published and unpublished works by Laura Kalpakian. Also included is a small amount of printed material collected by Laura Kalpakian.
Organization and Arrangement
Writings by Laura Kalpakian, including novels, short stories, reviews and freelance work, correspondence and material collected by Laura Kalpakian.
Women authors, American -- California, Southern -- Archives.; Kalpakian, Laura--Archives.
- Material Collected by Laura Kalpakian
  - Three issues of The Paper., 1980's (Box 17, Folder 6)
- Writings by Laura Kalpakian
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  SERIES CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access digital materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  - "Blue Willow" Email correspondence., 2003 March 6/2003 April (Box 16, Folder 7)
    Scope and Contents note
    "Blue Willow" in Good Housekeeping (vol.236, no.4).
  - Caveat (Box 14, Box 15)
    - Newspaper clipping - First draft., 1983/1984 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Writing process and publishing notes, 1986-2003 (Box 14, Folder 1, 3, 5)
      - Two early drafts., 2003 January/1986 (Box 14, Folder 1)
        Writing process and publishing notes refer to B14F1 - B14F2.
      - Draft no.2., [2003 January]/1993 (Box 14, Folder 3)
      - Complete manuscript - Notes., 2003 January/1993/1996 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Draft no.4 - Notes., 1993 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Copy edited draft - 2nd third of book., 1998 January - February (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Copy edited draft - Ch.1-8., n.d. (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Final draft (very different from book)., n.d. (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence with McCall's., 1987-1992 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Cosette (Box 7, Box 8, Box 9, Box 10, Box 11, Box 12, Box 13)
    - Chapter 11., 1994 August 22 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Writing process and publishing notes, 2003 January (Box 7, Box 8, Box 9, Box 10, Box 11, Box 12)
      - Writing materials overview, 2003 January (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Early drafts., 2003 January/n.d. (Box 7, Folder 2-5)
      - Drafts., 2003 January/1994 August (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
      - Drafts., 2003 January/1994 October 11 (Box 8, Folder 4-5)
      - Two thirds of novel - 3rd or 4th from final draft., 2003 January/1995 January (Box 9, Folder 1-3)
      - Book II last draft., [2003 January]/1995 January (Box 9, Folder 4)
      - Late hand-corrected drafts., [2003 January]/1995 January (Box 10, Folder 1-3)
      - Final draft from middle of book., [2003 January]/1995 January (Box 10, Folder 5)
      - Chapter 14 draft., [2003 January/1995 February] (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - Part of very late version., 2003 January/1995 January (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - LM II Arc., n.d. (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Corrections., n.d. (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - 2nd to last draft., 1995 February (Box 11, Folder 2-4)
    - British cover., n.d. (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Press packet., n.d. (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous documents - Correspondence - Notes to copy editor., [1995] (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Notes to copy editor., [1995] (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Dust jacket copy., [1995] (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Promotional display., n.d. (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Press coverage., 1994-1995 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Copy edited draft., 1995 March (Box 13, Folder 1-4)
  - Crescendo., [2003 January/February]/1985-1986 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    Writing process and publishing notes - Early notes.
  - Dark Continent., 2003 February/[1989] (Box 16, Folder 4)
    Writing process and publishing notes - Very early draft.
  - Delinquent Virgin (Box 5, Box 6)
    - Writing process and publishing notes., 2003 February (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - "A Brief Inquiry into the Origins of St. Elmo, California.", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Draft., n.d. (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Final., 1999 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - "How Maxwell Perkins Learned to Edit.", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - "Right Hand Man." (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - "A Brief Inquiry into the Origins of St. Elmo, California.", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - "Little Women.", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - "Cromwell's Castle" - Final., n.d. (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - "Change at Empoli.", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - "Moby Jack.", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - "A Long Story Short.", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - "Ethnic Cleansing.", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - "Change at Empoli" - Last draft., 1990 Spring (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Writing process and publishing notes, 1989-2003 (Box 6, Folder 2-5, 7)
      - "Little Women" - Draft., 2003 February/1989 September (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - "Right Hand Man" - Draft., 2003 February/1989 September 10 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - "Cromwell's Castle" - Final version., 2003 January/1993 July (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - "Change at Empoli" - Early drafts., [2003 January/February]/1990 February/1993 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - "A Brief Inquiry into the Origins of St. Elmo, California" - Drafts., [2003 January/February]/1991 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - "Change at Empoli" - Early drafts., 1990 February (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Copy editor's notes., n.d. (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - "A Brief Inquiry into the Origins of St. Elmo, California" - Three early drafts., n.d. (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Educating Waverly (Box 17, Box 18, Box 19, Box 20, Box 21)
    - Writing process and publishing notes - Correspondence., 2003 February/2001 August (Box 17, Folder 8)
      Writing process and publishing notes refer to B17F8 - B17F14.
    - Late drafts, 2000 (Box 17, Folder 9-14)
      - Part 1 - "The Time Being" - Chapter 1., 2000 August (Box 17, Folder 9)
      - Part 5 - "Defying Descartes" - Chapter 1., [2000 August] (Box 17, Folder 10)
      - Part 2 - "Dinner with the King of Sweden" - Chapter 1. (Box 17, Folder 11)
      - Part 4 - Chapter 1., 2000 August 8 (Box 17, Folder 12)
      - Part 3 - "Keeping Time" - Chapter 1., 2000 August 7 (Box 17, Folder 13)
      - Part 5 - "Defying Descartes" - Chapter 1., [2000 August] (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - Writing process and publishing notes., 2003 February 10 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Early drafts, 1999 (Box 18, Folder 2-26)
      - Part 2 - "Dinner with the King of Sweden" - Chapter 1., 1999 December 12 (Box 18, Folder 2)
      - [Parts of early chapters]., [1999] (Box 18, Folder 3)
      - Chapter 3., 1999 December 10 (Box 18, Folder 4)
      - Part 2 - "Dinner wit the King of Sweden" - Old Chapter 1., [1999] (Box 18, Folder 5)
      - Chapter 2., 1999 December 4 (Box 18, Folder 6)
      - Part 2 - Chapter 3., 1999 December 9 (Box 18, Folder 7)
      - Chapter 2., 1999 December 5 (Box 18, Folder 8)
      - Chapter 3., 1999 December 10 (Box 18, Folder 9)
      - Chapter 4 - Two versions., [1999] (Box 18, Folder 10)
      - Part 1 - "The Time Being" - Chapter 1 - Three versions., [1999] (Box 18, Folder 11)
      - Chapter 3 - Two versions., [1999] (Box 18, Folder 12)
      - Chapter 4., 1999 December 10 (Box 18, Folder 13)
      - Part 2 - "Dinner with the King of Sweden" - Chapter 1., [1999] (Box 18, Folder 14)
      - Part 2 - Chapter 2., 1999 December 12 (Box 18, Folder 15)
      - Part 2 - Chapter 3., [1999] (Box 18, Folder 16)
      - Chapter 4., [1999] (Box 18, Folder 17)
      - Part 1 - "The Time Being" - Final draft Chapter 1., 1999 December 13 (Box 18, Folder 18)
      - Chapter 4., [1999] (Box 18, Folder 19)
      - Part 2 - "Dinner with the King of Sweden" - Chapter 1., [1999] (Box 18, Folder 20)
      - Chapter 2 - Final draft., [1999] (Box 18, Folder 21)
      - Part 2 - Chapter 3., [1999] (Box 18, Folder 22)
      - Part 1 - Chapter 4., [1999] (Box 18, Folder 23)
      - Part 1 - "The Time Being" - Chapter 1., [1999] (Box 18, Folder 24)
      - Chapter 3., [1999] (Box 18, Folder 25)
      - Chapter 4., [1999] (Box 18, Folder 26)
    - "Educating Waverly (Tempo). August 2001 Drafts. 2nd to Last Drafts" (Box 19, Folder 1)
      One 3.5 inch floppy disk.
      Organization and Arrangement
      Contents of the disk have been printed and arranged by file in Folders 2-15. They are listed below.
      - Part 2 - "Dinner with the King of Sweden.", [2001 August] (Box 19, Folder 2)
        File title: "Dinner with the King."
      - Memo to copy editor., 2001 August 25 (Box 19, Folder 3)
        File title: "Copyed MEMO August 25."
      - Memo to Jennifer Hershey., 2001 August 25 (Box 19, Folder 4)
        File title: "JenMem EW Aug'01."
      - Part 3 - "The Maid of the Isles.", 2001 August 4 (Box 19, Folder 5)
        File title: "Maid of the Isles."
      - Part 1 - "The Temp and the Tempo.", [2001 August] (Box 19, Folder 6)
        File title: "Part 1 finrev '01."
      - Part 2 - "Dinner with the King of Sweden.", [2001 August] (Box 19, Folder 7)
        File title: "Part2fin."
      - Part 3 - "Maid of the Isles.", [2001 August] (Box 19, Folder 8)
        File title: "Part3finrev."
      - Part 4 - "The Time Being.", [2001 August] (Box 19, Folder 9)
        File title: "Part4finrev."
      - Part 5 - "Time After Time.", [2001 August] (Box 19, Folder 10)
        File title: "Part5finrev."
      - Part 6 - "Defying Descartes.", [2001 August] (Box 19, Folder 11)
        File title: "Part6 finrev."
      - Part 7 - "Tempo.", [2001 August] (Box 19, Folder 12)
        File title: "Part7 finrev."
      - Part 1 - "The Tempo & The Tempo" - Chapter 1., [2001 August 2] (Box 19, Folder 13)
        File title: "Temp& Tempo."
      - "Tempo" pages., [2001 August] (Box 19, Folder 14)
        File title: "Tempo pages."
      - Title possibilities., [2001 August] (Box 19, Folder 15)
        File title: "Title possibilities."
    - "Educating Waverly. LA Kalpakian. Spring '01 version (3rd to last)" (Box 21, Folder 1)
      Contents of the disk have been printed and arranged by file in Folders 2-7. They are listed below.
      - Part 1 - Final revision., 2001 April 26 (Box 21, Folder 2)
      - Part 2 - Revision., 2001 April 17 (Box 21, Folder 3)
      - Part 3 - Revision., 2001 April 27 (Box 21, Folder 4)
      - Part 4 - [Revision]., [2001] (Box 21, Folder 5)
      - Part 5 - Final draft of new version., [2001] April 27 (Box 21, Folder 6)
      - Part 6 - Final revision., 2001 April 27 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - "Educating Waverly by Laura Kalpakian. EW Toute Finale- 2002" (Box 21, Folder 8)
      Contents of the disk have been printed and arranged by file in Folders 9-18. They are listed below.
      - Copy editor's additional pages., [2002] (Box 21, Folder 9)
        File title: "Copyedit pages."
      - Opening pages., [2002] (Box 21, Folder 10)
        File title: "Opening pages."
      - Memo to Jennifer Hershey., 2001 October 29 (Box 21, Folder 11)
        File title: "Return to NY memo."
      - Part 1 - "The Temp and the Tempo.", [2001] (Box 21, Folder 12)
      - Part 2 - "Dinner with the King of Sweden.", [2002] (Box 21, Folder 13)
      - Part 3 - "Maid of the Isles.", [2002] (Box 21, Folder 14)
      - Part 4 - "The Time Being.", [2002] (Box 21, Folder 15)
      - Part 5 - "Time After Time.", [2002] (Box 21, Folder 16)
      - Part 6 - "Defying Descartes.", [2002] (Box 21, Folder 17)
      - Part 7 - "Tempo.", [2002] (Box 21, Folder 18)
    - "Educating Waverly by Laura Kalpakian. Old Tempo- 1st version on computer. (Some duplication?)" (Box 20, Folder 1)
      Contents of the disk have been printed and arranged by file in Folders 2-11. They are listed below.
      - Part 1 - "Time Out of Mind.", 2000 August 5 (Box 20, Folder 2)
        File title: "Tempo#1p."
      - Part 2 - "Dinner with the King of Sweden.", [2000 August] (Box 20, Folder 3)
        File title: "Tempo#2d."
      - Part 3 - "Keeping Time.", [2000 August] (Box 20, Folder 4)
        File title: "Temp#3."
      - Part 5 - "Maid of the Isles.", [2000 August] (Box 20, Folder 5)
        File title: "Temp#4."
      - Part 6 - "Defying Descartes.", [2000 August] (Box 20, Folder 6)
        File title: "Temp#5de."
      - Part 1 - "The Time Being.", 2000 July 30 (Box 20, Folder 7)
        File title: "Prt 1 2000 draft."
      - Tempo Part 2 - "Dinner with the King of Sweden.", [2000] (Box 20, Folder 8)
        File title: "Tempop~1."
      - Part 7 - "The Time Being.", [2000] (Box 20, Folder 9)
        File title: "Tempconclu."
      - Part 7 - "The Time Being.", [2000] (Box 20, Folder 10)
        File title: "Tempocon."
      - "Tempo" pages., [2000] (Box 20, Folder 11)
        File title: "Tempopag."
  - Fair Agosto (Box 16, Folder 1-2)
    - Draft., 1982 February (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Writing process and publishing notes - Late draft., 2003 January/1987 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Graced Land (Box 1, Box 2, Box 3, Box 4, Box 5)
    - Writing process and publishing notes., 2003 February 3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence - Post copy edit., 1991 October (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Notes and other writing materials., 1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Elvis photograph postcard., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - General notes., [1991] (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence regarding cover art., 1991 November 15 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - The writing of Graceland (sic)., 1991 January (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Dust jacket copy (Two versions)., 1991 February (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Earliest draft., [1990] (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Early draft - Cilla., [1990] (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Part 1 - Final draft., 1991 June - July (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - A Catholic Country - 2nd to last draft., 1991 January (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Revised mark-up - Emily 1st., 1990 September (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Emily mark-up., [1990] July (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Old Maid's Prayer to Gail - I., [1990] (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Starlight Coupe to Gail - II., [1990] (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - The Book of Acts to Gail - III., 1991 January 12 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Burning Love to Gail - IV., 1991 January 15 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Shake, Rattle and Roll to Gail - V., 1991 January 12 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Chapter 20., [1991] (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Final revisions - Chapter 5., 1991 August (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Final revisions - Chapters 9-15., 1991 August (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Final revisions - Complete draft., [1991] (Box 3, Folder 2-4)
    - Final draft - Part 2., 1991 August (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Final draft before revision., 1991 January (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
    - Complete draft for agent search., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
    - The Book of Love original., [1991 January] (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Final draft - Old Maid's Prayer., 1991 January 11 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - The Book of Love to Gail., 1991 January 19 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Burning Love - I., [1991] (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Shake, Rattle and Roll - 2., [1991] (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Final corrections - Starlight Coupe., 1991 January (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Final corrections - Book of Acts., 1991 January (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Haunting of Phyllis C. Farnsworth (The) - Writing process and publishing notes., [2003 January/February]/1980's (Box 17, Folder 4)
    Near to last draft.
  - Laws of Gravity (The) - Writing process and publishing notes., 2003 January/1984 February (Box 17, Folder 7)
    Early draft.
  - Lonesome Highway (The)., 1982 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    "The Lonesome Highway" in Mickle Street Review no.4.
  - Scents and Sensibility - Writing process and publishing notes., [2003 January/February]/1989 November (Box 17, Folder 5)
    Early drafts.
  - Solitary Pleasures/Truce - Writing process and publishing notes., 1980's (Box 17, Folder 5)
    Late or final drafts.
  - Steps & Ex's - Writing process and publishing notes. (Box 15, Folder 3-7)
    - Old draft., 2003 January/1998 Summer (Box 15, Folder 3-4)
    - Correspondence w/ copy editor - Copy edited final draft., 2003 January/1998 September 17/1998 July (Box 15, Folder 5-7)
- Overview of Materials
  - Overview of materials - Publishing history - Curriculum Vitae., 2003 January (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Note on copyright and permissions., 2003 January (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Reviews and freelance., v.d. (Box 16, Folder 8)